last evening the Finance Minister spoke
about the possibility of the economy
Contracting this year and growth
Contracting this year because of an act
of God for some reason there is great
surprise and consternation at this
statement one wonders why considering
that the Reserve Bank of India has said
not once but several times that they
expect the economy to contract this year
because of the C ID 19 pandemic no one
knows for sure by how much we may get
the fast inkling of how bad it got on
Monday when the quarter 1 GDP numbers
will be out now there are a number of
estimates out there on how much the
economy can shrink as of an ET now poll
it can shrink as much as
19% this quarter that also tells you how
deep the pain is for the because of the
Corona virus pandemic and how shaky the
recovery has been so far we've seen some
recovery in the month of June it peted
out in July because of localized and
frequent lockdowns there is no great
respite in August we will know if the
economy unlocks further in September
guidelines are expected uh by the end of
this month and that may give us a clue
to what is happening later on but how
crucial are these q1 GDP numbers will
the data have been collected also
correctly can it be assessed correctly
considering that there was a lockdown on
for a lot of that period to speak on
some of these factors I'm joined today
by Mr subash Chandra gar former Finance
secretary and uh Mr NR banam morti Vice
Chancellor of the basc University
Bengaluru welcome to both of you and
thank you for speaking with us on the
show this evening Mr gar your first take
on basically the data on Monday that
everyone's going to look for you know
whenever we talk about GDP data some
people have the view that too much
importance is given to it because it
talks about what has already gone by it
comes in with a lag effect do you think
this time around there are crucial Clues
uh to what lies in the future which will
be there to glean from this
data GDP is an extremely important
number number it tells you what the
entire country has earned as income it
is the income of the labor Capital
government everything depends on GDP how
much do you consume how much do you
spend on New Capital constructions and
all so GDP is not an simple number it's
an extremely important
phenomenon GDP keeps on evolving today
in this world when there are so much of
data which is available virtually being
generated online in real time you get a
much better sense of where the uh GDP or
the growth is heading uh but it needs to
be officially sort of confirmed that
where we are and that is why the number
which is going to be announced on on
Monday for the first quarter is an
extremely important number uh the
government may have a system where the
data collection might have been somewhat
affected but today the data is the
biggest biggest asset available so you
will have a good sense just to respond
to what you initially said about the act
of God and
contraction I think no one in this world
believes that there would not be a
contraction of the Indian economy
everybody believes that there would be a
contraction what makes what differs is
the estimation of the amount of
contraction and this was caused by two
principal
factors which is not the act of God
directly one is the
covid-19 that hit everyone that hit lot
of people lot of businesses Airlines
can't function many of other businesses
can't
function and the second the decision
taken by the government to import was a
certain kind of lockdown India witnessed
one of the biggest and the most
stringent lockdown so these were the two
reasons responsible for the contraction
how much contraction in my judgment in
the first quarter we would have
something close to about 25% of the
economy uh uh contraction in this first
quarter I can explain but I would do it
later in case you need but in my
judgment it's about 25% plusus
5% all right
I'll come back to you on that uh Mr
garan I'm Keen to understand why you've
come to the 25% figure you're not the
only one there are host of agencies of
course who put out their estimate and
they range between 15% to 25% uh but let
me get in Professor banam morti for his
take how crucial do you think these
numbers are will they also give us a
sense of how steep the recovery needs to
be I mean I'm not going into the whole
you know tick versus V versus slow curve
or whoo or what kind of shape the
recovery will be but it also gives us a
sense of how deep that cut is at the end
of the day that calculation will be made
because whatever you may say and today
India is close to 880,000 Fresh cases
our fatality rates our mortality rates
from covid have been lesser than
everyone predicted uh in the end of
March and in early April it was expected
to be much much worse thankfully it's
not and one of those reasons could be
attributed to the extreme harsh lockdown
we will see the other side of it on
Monday well um I broadly agree with Mr
G's you know view on the GDP numbers um
having um worked on the methodology of
um revising the GDP numbers for almost
10 years with the ministry of Statistics
I would like to say that uh predicting
the quarterly numbers even during the
normal times are very very
risky now leave alone the covid
situation and um in fact um when we were
doing this assessment we were telling
something close to what Mr GGA said like
minus 25% but certainly we were not
predicting that we basically that was an
assumption uh looking at some of the sub
sectors the trends that is coming from
some of the sub sectors so this is not
the time in my view to forecast the
quarterly GDP numbers and um I'm happy
that institutions like RBI has kept away
in from doing these kind of projections
now you have already seen uh the kind of
the range of forecast from % to minus
37% you know you cannot get that kind of
a range by whatever the model that
you're using now having said that um
again as Mr G pointed out the first
quarter of the current Financial year
there is no way you can expect any great
number uh but since um the way the
methodology of quarterly GDP numbers
most of the components that are used in
estimating the quarterly GDP numbers are
the forecasts forecast based on the
previous quarter or whatever the
previous to previous quarter information
so I think um uh you might see a sharp
revision from what they are going to say
on Monday and when when we get the final
numbers maybe at the end of the
financial year um I would expect uh the
GDP growth would have bottomed out in
the first quarter of the current
Financial year uh for the reason that
you already pointed out Tam and we
should be expecting a you know uh turn
turn in the overall GDP number from the
second quarter you may still see a
negative numbers but um as I've been
arguing for quite some time the recovery
is going to be much more slower than
what everybody is predicting um uh but
then it all depends but all the forecast
I want to I want to make it very clear
the forecast are always conditional
about most of the policy intervention
that we make now government of India as
as well as RBI has brought out many many
policy measures but it all depends on
how all those measures are going to be
implemented how it is going to be
realized and I think that will determine
what would be the GDP shape going to be
from the second quarter of the
financials
you know I I think the reason that
nobody is even uh attempting to do that
because as you said implementation is
one factor but one can argue that
implementation is still in our control
you know hopefully if implementation is
done well there could be some recovery
but something like stopping the spread
of the virus or understanding what can
come next I mean there was a report a
few days ago about one individual who
had been reinfected now that is
something people didn't know about when
will the vaccine come Etc there too many
imponderables there but let me come back
to one very interesting thing that Mr
gar said you predict a
25% contraction in quarter 1 uh our
internal poll says about 19% you're at
actually the uh upper end of that range
of predictions out there please explain
Mr gar how have you come to this figure
and what is the basis of your estimate
see the uh the there are four major
components of uh GDP from the
consumption side the private consumption
the government consumption and the
investment uh and the export import kind
of thing the capital investment uh is
about 30% of GDP that is practically
flat neither is the investment taking
place in manufacturing nor in
infrastructure and at a very very
reduced scale in the first quarter when
there was a lockdown
so that was the segment which was
massively impacted so 30% of the
contributing GDP was I don't think it
was more than
onethird functional at that time look at
the other one the consumption in the
consumption which is about 60% the
private consumption which is about 60%
of the
GDP there are two large large segments
one is the discretionary consumption and
the the other one is the non-
discretionary consumption the
discretionary consumption is about 20
25% out of
60% that had also totally Fallen flat
there was no discretionary consumptions
on travel on Fashion on purchase of uh
luxury items and other kind of things so
uh that had also contracted in that
quarter by something close to 50 to 60
or maybe more more percent it was the uh
the compulsory or the non-discretionary
consumption which was holding up
reasonably well was everybody has to eat
has to sort of consume other minimum
services like like electricity Etc which
were also to some extent impacted and
the government consumption was somewhat
higher so if you put these all four
elements together and exports and
imports were also down you would come to
this number that about 25% of the
economic activity did not take place
this is also born out if you look at the
corporate numbers which they have
reported uh on on the turnover side if
you look at the the the uh production of
the items look at automobiles look at
the retail and anything so whole lot of
data seems to be pointing out very
clearly that there was about 25% sort of
output loss consumption loss
investment loss and consequential income
loss which is also reflected by you you
look at the number of people who went
out the job in in the month of April and
May and all so I think taking it all
together and I my analysis suggests that
25% is a a fair estimate of the
contraction for the first
quarter um Mr G I also want to get you
know your take on the kind of recovery
that India has seen um in a comparative
state covid-19 has hit the whole world
different countries adopted different
approaches on how to tackle with it
India went down into a sharper lockdown
much earlier then unlocked we also have
a large population so a huge number of
cases Etc large recoveries as well when
you compare the economic recovery in in
India and with other nations where do
you see
us so the uh unlock down was the most
necessary decision and we started
unlocking from the middle of May and
slowly slowly we have put most of the
economy back on the rails but still
there are quite a few things which are
affected you don't have metros you don't
get the transportation means operating
at capacity School other things are
still so there is some part of the
entertainment uh and other activities
are still under some sort of lockdown
but if you put it that about 80 to 85%
of the economy has been allowed to be
operated uh in a normal sense now that
uh uh is the comforting factor that that
would put the economy back on Rails uh
gradually and we have now two months
gone by of the second quarter of also so
we have some sense of where the economic
activi is taking place in July and
August but the Dynamics is much more
sort of complex you have to see whether
the demand has come back whether the
supply disruptions which are caused by
uh not only lockdown but the local
lockdowns and many other factors the
labor is still not fully back at at at
places of work the construction activi
is also affected the demand for certain
kind of things has come down so in my
judgment after the the unlocking is
playing its part you saw the pr of dama
demand coming up in in the month of June
then there was some s some sort of pling
which is being sort of seen in the month
of July and August so in my sense the
recovery has started taking place but
the second quarter would also seem a a
reasonably good contraction it's only in
the third quarter that perhaps we may
come a little more closer to to the uh
economic normal economic function I
don't see before the fourth quarter the
economy coming back
into a normal state or at the activity
level as at the last year incidentally
in last year the uh the lockdown started
in month of March so last year
um economic growth was also to some
extent muted so my sens is and I'm
making very broad estimates these are
subject to as you said how how the and
as bhanu said how the economic decisions
or the policy decisions which have been
taken play out in my judgment we'll
probably see uh about a 15% contraction
in second quarter about 5 to 7% in the
third quarter and in the fourth quarter
probably we'll be uh at at the at the
level at which we were there in the last
last year that's why I have been on
record saying that the
year 2021 probably we'll see a very
large contraction for the year as a
whole of about
10%
yes okay so that's that's you know
you've stuck your neck out there and put
out all of those figures of course you
have the disclaimer that all of us have
right now which is of the act of God we
don't know what is going to happen up
ahead so that gives us some courage to
go out and make those predictions Mr
bhamori can I tempt you to make some
predictions as well or should I just
restrict you to uh you know talking
about uh the impact that the festive
season may have on uplifting quarter 2
well um I think um I have been in this
profession of forecasting for almost 20
years um two decades and that really
makes me to be little more careful about
doing forecasting and um I've been doing
this quarterly modeling monthly annual
so I've been doing a lot of forecasting
work for quite some time so um in fact
what is more interesting right now is
not really the number per se uh what is
the GDP growth going to be for the whole
year I think that is we still have to
wait for some some time as as you
rightly say Act of God we don't know
what is going to happen in the next
couple of months or quarters but I think
what is more important right now is what
are the policies that we need to really
put in place to you know help Revival of
the economy I think that's that should
be the most important thing that we need
to think about now we have done some
simulations I don't do forecasting
because of these uncertain conditions
but we have done some simulations I
think there is a difference between
forecast and the simulation so we have
done some simulations the kind of
current policy intervention that we have
we already have in place now if they all
have you know implemented I think the
GDP growth for the whole year would not
be I mean very uh the kind of negative
number that is being floated I would say
much more decent number I'm I'm still
not going to put the number for this but
we are going to see a much much decent
number than what most of the forecasters
are saying but again as I'm saying it is
subject to uh the policy um uh
implementation but I think for more than
GDP numbers I more concerned about the
outcome of all these policy measur that
is an inflation right now we need to
more worry more about inflation um well
you might have you know go for a uh you
know second stimulus but then if it
leads to only improving only the demand
conditions I think we are going to see a
inflationary pressure in the IND economy
we need to focus more on the supply side
measures and that is one of the reasons
why um you know how do we explain this
7% inflation right now now there is a
demand we don't know the demand is
happening but we don't know to what
extent Supply is happening but if you
look at the gap between demand and
Supply I'm sure there is increase in
demand but at the same time there is no
catch up in terms of the supply I think
that is one of the reasons why you are
seeing High inflationary pressure for
almost 6 to 7 months so we need to
really tackle the supply side issues
right now urgently uh if at all you want
to see uh better outcomes of the policy
interventions right
now well absolutely uh you know you've
uh given a sort of a broad uh estimate
there that it will be better the GDP
number for the year will be better than
what was expected well we don't know
what everyone is expecting ing uh but
we'll try and take away some optimism
from there meanwhile let's wait and
watch what happens on Monday thank you
so much Mr gar and Professor banam morti
for joining us on this very very
important discussion well talking about
economic models followed around the
world and talked about all around the
world we must talk today about abenomics
coined after the Japanese prime
minister's policy Shinzo Abbe who today
has announced that he will be stepping
down he will be the longest serving
Prime Minister of Japan and is stepping
down due to ill health he will be
leaving behind a legacy that will be
remembered Japan's longest serving prime
minister shinzu a is preparing to hang
up his boots the reason is ill health
Abbe who's currently 65 has suffered
from alterative colitis which is an
inflammatory bow disease that he had
since he was a teenager but the illness
had resurfaced recently and had worsened
in fact it was because of this disease
that he abruptly resigned in the year
20072 from an earlier term as prime
minister only to return in a landslide
victory in the year 2012 since then Abe
has been firmly in control of Japan's
economic
future AB tenure has been marked by
efforts to revive Japan's economy
through a policy package known as
abenomics which was launched in the year
2013 abenomics was based on a
three-pronged approach higher spending
from the government lose monetary policy
from the bank of Japan and a package of
structural reforms to raise the longr
Run growth rate of the economy the goal
was to rescue the country from two
decades of near stagnation and permanent
deflation opinion on how well abenomics
has worked is divided critics say that L
monre policy was not backed with enough
structural reform While others agree
that Japan has seen better growth under
a recently the US China trade War has
posed fresh economic challenges to Japan
AB will also be stepping down at a time
when his response to the Corona virus
pandemic is under intense scrutiny
critics have called his initial response
to the outbreak clumsy and point out
that there has been more emphasis on
economy rather than health for Indians
the bonomi between prime minister
Narendra Modi and Shinzo AB stand out
with both leaders working towards closer
ties AB will continue in his position I
until a successor is found and he's sure
to leave behind a legacy as a leader
whose shocking or economic policies have
been admire the world over with Nagi
Vikram MOA in Mumbai for
E9 we'll take a very short break on the
show when we come back we are turning
our Focus to real estate and you will
hear from the big voice of the day our
exclusive conversation with perosa godri
the executive chairman of godri
properties does he see some hope for the
reality sector we'll find out after this
very short break